Guide to the Edwin Rice Papers
Museum of Innovation and Science
Edwin W. Rice Jr. Papers
1862 - 1935
Documents created and collected by Edwin W. Rice, jr., President of General Electric from 1913 until 1922. This collection contains multiple accessions, which include working papers and correspondence from Rice's career and personal life.
6 cubic ft.
Rice, Edwin Wilbur, 1862-
Creation of this finding aid was supported by a grant from the Center for History of Physics, American Institute of Physics.
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Edwin Wilbur Rice, Jr., was born in 1862, the son of Edwin Rice, a missionary of the American Sunday-School Union, who settled in Philadelphia in 1871 and became assistant director of missions and editor of the Union’s publications. In Philadelphia, Edwin Rice, Jr. was a high school student of Elihu Thomson’s. After high school he joined Thomson in his venture into the electrical industry, first at the American Electrical Company and then the reorganized Thomson-Houston Company, which moved to Lynn, Massachusetts in 1883. Rice was a capable technician who received nearly 100 patents in his lifetime, but his strength lay in management of manufacturing and engineering.
At Thomson-Houston, Rice was made factory manager of the Lynn plant. Upon the formation of General Electric in 1892, he was named Technical Director for the company. In 1896 he became vice-president in charge of manufacturing and engineering. Rice made the suggestion to acquire Eickemeyer & Osterheld for both its railway motor patents and its young engineer, Charles Steinmetz in 1892. Upon Steinmetz’s recommendation, Rice convinced GE President Charles Coffin to establish the GE Research Lab in 1900, to protect its valuable lamp business.
Rice became company president in 1913 upon the retirement of Coffin, who remained chairman of the company. In 1917 Rice added to his achievements with his election as president of the American Institute of Electrical Engineers (AIEE). He retired in 1922 as one of the elder statesmen of the electrical industry, and was interested in recording the history of the industry and its pioneers. Rice’s family was also highly involved in the company. Son Chester Rice, an engineer, was involved in the development of the loudspeaker, sonar, the sonic altimeter for airplanes, and the halogen leak detector. Edwin’s brother Martin P. managed GE’s Publicity Department.
Rice, Edwin Wilbur, 1862-
Notebooks, correspondence, published articles, and company publications from Edwin Rice’s employment at both Thomson-Houston and General Electric. Also includes a number of books from Rice’s personal library concerning electricity and engineering. Several notebooks in the collection are from a turbine-generator salesman, M.C. Olson, with data dating from about 1918-1931. Highlights of the correspondence include letters from Thomas Edison, Elihu Thomson, Frank Sprague, James J. Wood, and other electrical pioneers that were intended for use as a preface for John W. Hammond’s history of GE, Men and Volts. There are also correspondence, scripts, and plans for Thomas Edison’s 1922 visit to Schenectady and a 1927 interview between Rice and Edison for the AIEE.
Most of the notebooks date back to Thomson-Houston, and include lists and specifications on Thomson-Houston dynamos and central station plants, the overall labor account for the company, and copies of electric railway patents held by Thomson-Houston in 1891. From General Electric come notebooks relating to the development of the Curtis steam turbine; Rice’s tracking of manufacturing space, employees and costs as vice-president; and technical data and sketches from his tenure as technical Director. Also included are Rice’s personal copies of Thomson-Houston and General Electric product supply catalogs, and an account book for Rice’s farm in Rexford, NY.
A second accession includes additional business and personal correspondence, GE historical notes, several of Rice’s technical notebooks, a payroll book from Thomson-Houston, receipts documenting his household expenses and Rice’s 1878 high school notebook from Elihu Thomson’s class at Central High School in Philadelphia.
- Articles: historical and technical, 1886 - 1959
- Books, 1893 - 1924
- Correspondence, 1882 - 1937
- Correspondence: GE history, Thomson-Houston, 1878 - 1933
- Correspondence: GE management payroll info, 1880 - 1933
- Library of Electric Science: (four volumes of six), 1902 - 1904
- Notebooks, 1892 - 1933
- Subject Files: Thomas Edison, GE history, 1903 - 1936
- Subject Files: Thomson-Houston, 1882 - 1930
- 2nd Accession: Box 1: American Electric, Thomson Houston, General Electric (1892-1922), correspondence with Elihu Thomson, 1883 - 1934
- 2nd Accession: Box 2: Publications, notes about contemporaries, personal financial, 1888 - 1935
- 2nd Accession: Box 3: 1910s- 1930s, 1915 - 2003
- 2nd Accession: Box 4: Estate, finances, and late 20s correspondence, 1910 - 1961
- 2nd Accession: Box 5: Notebooks and Diaries, 1918 - 1934
- 2nd Accession: Box 6: Family and Investments, 1862 - 1932
- 2nd Accession: Box 7: Helen Katherine Doen Rice (Kate), 1880 - 1896
- 2nd Accession: Box 8: Alice and family, 1878 - 1919
- 2nd Accession: Box 9: Family, 1897 - 1976
- 2nd Accession: Box 10: Alice and E.W. 1920-1960, 1911 - 1960
- 2nd Accession: Box 11: Chester Rice, Helen Currier, Lovejoy Family, 1880 - 2002
- 2nd Accession: Box 12: Rice family correspondence from Dan Griffin, 1889 - 1897
- 2nd Accession: Box 13: Photographs, 1880 - 1932
- 2nd Accesion: Box 14: photographs, 1874 - 1920
- 2nd Accession: Box 15: Photographs, 1904 - 1925
- 2nd Accession: Box 16: Oversize- Photo Albums, 1911 - 1941
- 2nd Accession: Box 17: Oversize- Photos, 1889 - 1922
- 2nd Accession: Box 18: Oversize photos, 1899
- 2nd Accession: Box 19: Blueprints, 1888 - 1929
- 2nd Accession: Box 20: Oversize photos, 1918